Register of the John K. Emmerson Papers, 1931-1985
Hoover Institution Archives
- SUBJECT FILE, 1937-1984
  - Japan
    - Allied occupation, Outline, 1945-1952. n.d. (Folder 7)
    - Defense (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - "Japan's Defense Policy -- Yesterday, Today and Tomorrow" by Hisao Iwashima, June, 1974
        - Japanese press summaries from the American Embassy in Japan
        - 1969 (Folder 2)
        - 1970 (Folder 3)
        - 1971 (Folder 4)
        - 1972 (Folder 5)
        - 1973 (Folder 6)
        - 1974 (Folder 7)
        - 1975 (Folder 8-9)
        - 1976 (Folder 10)
        - 1977 (Folder 11)
        - 1978 (Folder 12)
        - 1979 (Folder 13)
    - Economic conditions. Japanese press summaries from the American Embassy in Japan,; "Japan in a New Era of Change" by Kogoro Uemura, January, miscellaneous printed material, 1972-1978 1974; 1974, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Emperor. Japanese press summaries from the American Embassy in Japan,; background information, "The Imperial Family of Japan", memoranda for the Emperor's visit to U.S., 1973, 1975 1975; n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Energy
      - General. Correspondence, memoranda, notes on Japanese energy shortage, 1980 (Folder 3)
      - Oil. Japanese press summaries from the American Embassy in Japan,; U.S. Foreign Broadcast Information Service, memorandum by Yoshizane Iwasa, "The Oil Crisis and Japan", "Department Testifies on Arab Oil Embargoes", Department of State Bulletin, 1973-1975 1973, 1974; December 22, 1973; December 24, 1973 (Folder 4)
    - Foreign relations
      - General. Japanese press summaries from the American Embassy in Japan,; miscellaneous photocopies of printed material; memorandum of conversation, Emmerson and others, on Japanese Security Policy, Yomiuri Round-table Discussion, 1972-1978 August 4, 1969; August 31, 1969 (Folder 5-6)
      - China. Japanese press summaries from the American Embassy in Japan,; printed material, "Japan-China Rapprochement and Its Economic Impact", by Jiro Tokuyama and Masayoshi Oiso, Joint Statement of Japan and China, U.S. Department of State Telegram, 1970-1973 1970; November 7, 1972; September 29, 1972 (Folder 7)
      - Korea. Japanese press summaries from the American Embassy in Japan, notes, translation of meetings between President Kim Il Sung and Representative Tokuma Utsunomiya, 1977; 1970; August 9 and l0, 1974 (Folder 8)
      - U.S.S.R. Japanese press summaries from the American Embassy in Japan, 1970-1976 (Box 28, Folder 1-3)
      - United States (Folder 4-7)
        - General. Japanese press summaries,; address by Nobuhiko Ushiba, Ambassador to the U.S., press release, announcement on talks between Ambassador Robert Ingersoll and Deputy Vice Minister for Foreign Affiars Kiyohiko Tsurumi, text of U.S.-Japan Joint Communique, Japan-U.S. Relations -- Present Patterns and the Next Decade, printed material, notes, 1970-1978 February 16, 1973; September l, 1972; August 2, 1973; n.d.; 1970, 1973
        - Security treaty. Japanese press summaries,; address by H.E. Nobuhiko Ushiba, Ambassador to the U.S., "The Japanese-American Alliance: America's Asian Pandora's Box" by Donald C. Hellman, printed materials, 1972-1976 January 10, 1972; ca. 1972 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - Free speech. Notes, printed material, 1974 (Folder 2)
      - Kyoto. Japanese press summaries, 1973 (Folder 3)
      - Lockheed Case. Japanese press summaries, 1976 (Folder 4)
      - Miscellany (Folder 5)
      - Nishiyama Takehiko. Personal sketch, remarks, October 22, 1982 (Folder 6)
      - Nuclear energy and nuclear weapons. Japanese press summaries,; statements by M. Nisibori, 1972-1978 1973-1974 (Folder 7-9)
      - Politics and government (Box 30, Folder 1-3)
        - General. Japanese press summaries,; lineup of new cabinet and election results, printed material; "Japan, Current Political and Economic Developments", report prepared for Levi Strauss International Group, draft and typescript, 1970-1978 1966; March 18, 1977
        - Communist Party. Japanese press summaries, Foreign Broadcast Information Service, miscellaneous printed material
          - 1970 (Folder 4)
          - 1971 (Folder 5-6)
          - 1972 (Box 31, Folder 1)
          - 1973 (Folder 2-3)
          - 1974 (Folder 4)
          - 1975 (Folder 5)
          - 1977 (Folder 6)
          - 1978 (Folder 7)
        - Constitution. Japanese press summaries, 1973 (Box 32, Folder 1)
        - Elections. Japanese press summaries, printed material, notes
          - 1969 (Folder 2)
          - 1971 (Folder 3)
          - 1974 (Folder 4)
          - 1976 (Folder 5)
          - 1977 (Folder 6)
        - Political parties. Japanese press summaries, notes, 1972, 1978 (Folder 7)
        - Polls. Japanese press summaries, 1973-1978 (Folder 8)
        - Sato Eisaku. Program of his visit to the United States, joint statement with President Lyndon B. Johnson, speech at National Press Club, Washington, D.C., Sato-Nixon Communique, notes; Sato-Nixon Statement, meeting at San Clemente, November 12-19, 1967, November 15, 1967; November 21, 1969; November 2, 1969, January 9, 1972; January 6-7, 1972 (Folder 9)
        - Tanaka Kakuei. "The Rise and Decline of Tanaka Kakuei: The Problem of 'Structural Corruption' in the Japanese Political System" by Chalmers Johnson, text of a joint statement following meetings between Prime Minister Kakuei Tanaka and President Richard Nixon, Hawaii,; "Research on Kakuei Tanaka -- His Money Veins and Personnel Veins" by Takashi Tachibana, November 2, 1983; August 31-September 1, 1972 October, 1974 (Folder 10)
      - Ryukyu Islands
        - Okinawa. Japanese press summaries, 1970-1974 (Folder 11)
        - Sensaku. Japanese press summaries,; report (incomplete), 1970-1972 n.d. (Folder 12)
      - Science and technology. Japanese press summaries, 1977 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - Territorial waters and fishing rights. Japanese press summaries, 1977 (Folder 2)
      - Trade. Japanese press summaries,; printed materials, "Economic Trends in Japan and Their Implications for the United States" from the American Embassy, Tokyo, to the Department of State, (photocopy), 1972-1978 1971-1972; December 14, 1972 (Folder 3)
      - Trade unions. Foreign Broadcast Information Service issuances,; printed material, notes, 1970-1974 1974 (Folder 4)
      - World War II. Outlines, "Road to War", "Peace Treaty With Japan" (Folder 5)
    - Japan-America Student Conference. Correspondence, notes, articles of incorporation, programs, itineraries, printed material, memoranda, 1969-1979 (Folder 6-7)
    - Japan Center for International Exchange. Correspondence, report on major programs and activities, itinerary, 1976-1978 (Folder 8)
    - Japan Society. Correspondence, guest list, printed material, memoranda, membership lists, balance sheet, proposal, 1966-1984 (Folder 9)
    - Japanese studies. Correspondence, notes, forms, reports, summary of joint committee, 1972 (Folder 10)
    - Kissinger, Henry. Japanese press summaries, news release on visit to Asia, transcript of news conference, text of communique and transcript of news conference, Department of State Bulletin,; "The U.S. and Japan in a Changing World", speech; "Constancy and Change in American Foreign Policy", speech, 1972-1973; February 27, 1973; April 30, 1975; March 19, 1973 June 18, 1975, June 23, 1975 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Korea. Japanese press summaries, printed materials; travel materials, brochures, memoranda, correspondence related to John K. Emmerson's trip to Korea for United States International Communication Agency, schedule for conference on Korea at George Washington University, 1974-1975; 1980; May 1-3, 1975 (Folder 2)
    - Malaysia. Background notes, U.S. Department of State, 1966 (Folder 3)
    - Mid-Atlantic Clubs. Membership list, agenda, 1974 (Folder 4)
    - Miscellany (Folder 5)
    - National Institute for Research Advancement. Correspondence, memoranda, proposal, 1976-1977 (Folder 6)
    - Nigeria. "Nigeria and the British Cameroons", background information, 1960 (Folder 7)
    - Okinawa. Correspondence, proposal, notes, printed material, reports, 1965-1972 (Folder 8-9)
    - Pacific Basin Economic Council. Memoranda, reference materials, printed materials, notes, 1973 (Folder 10)
    - Philippine Islands. Background notes, U.S. Department of State, 1966 (Folder 11)
    - San Francisco Committee on Foreign Relations. Correspondence, memoranda, membership list, 1981 (Folder 12)
    - Southeast Asia. Japanese press summaries, 1969-1976 (Folder 13)
    - Stanford University (Box 35)
      - General
        - General (Folder 1)
        - Foreign visitors (Folder 2)
        - Graduates in U.S. government (Folder 3)
      - Alumni Association. Correspondence, memoranda, printed materials, itineraries, etc. related to John K. Emmerson's participation in Travel/Study programs, 1979-1982 (Folder 4-12)
      - Berkeley-Stanford East Asian Studies. Newsletter, memoranda, course outline, 1974-1975 (Folder 13)
      - East Asia Studies Theme House. Memoranda, statement, 1983 (Folder 14)
      - ASSU Guest Professorship. Correspondence, memoranda, 1982-1983 (Folder 15)
      - Center for East Asian Studies. Correspondence, memoranda, faculty lists, 1972-1975 (Box 36, Folder 1)
      - Center for Research in International Studies. Correspondence, memoranda, newsletter, language and course listing, research proposals, 1974-1981 (Folder 2-6)
      - Center for International Security and Arms Control. Correspondence, memoranda, agenda, project reports, conference participants, reports, papers, notes, 1974-1979 (Folder 7-10)
      - Center for International Security and Arms Control. Correspondence, memoranda, agenda, project reports, papers, notes, preliminary proposals, research materials, working paper, 1969-1979 (Box 37, Folder 1-5)
      - History Department. Correspondence, memoranda, course outlines, notes, student lists, book lists, student papers, 1966-1973 (Folder 6)
      - Miscellany (Box 38, Folder 1)
      - Northeast Asia-U.S. Forum. Correspondence, memoranda, 1979-1981 (Folder 2)
      - Office of Admissions. Correspondence, recommendation forms, 1982 (Folder 3)
      - Political Science Department. Correspondence, course outlines, book lists, notes, student lists, 1967-1973 (Folder 4)
      - Project on U.S.-Japan Relations. Correspondence, memoranda, printed material, membership lists, proposals, 1974-1979 (Folder 5)
      - Public Affairs Fellowship Program. Correspondence, memoranda, 1970-1975 (Folder 6)
      - Sierra Camp. Correspondence, notes, participants lists, 1979 (Folder 7)
      - State Department Visiting Fellows. Correspondence, memoranda, 1967-1970 (Folder 8)
      - Workshops on Political and Social Issues (SWOPSI). Course outlines, course notices, 1979 (Folder 9)
    - Stanford Research Institute. Correspondence, project team report, printed material, proposal, 1969-1972 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Taiwan. Japanese press summaries, printed material, notes, 1972-1980 (Folder 2)
    - Takayanagi, Kenzo. "Reminiscences of Professor Takayanagi" by Thomas L. Blakemore, May 27, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - Thailand. "Thailand -- Long Form" (Folder 4)
    - Toyota Foundation. Correspondence, memoranda, biographical notes, 1976-1977 (Folder 5)
    - Trilateral Commission. Correspondence, newsletter, joint statement, printed material, 1974 (Folder 6)
    - U.S.S.R. Japanese press summaries; World Affairs Report on the XXVth Congress of the Communist Party of the U.S.S.R.; printed material, 1970-1977 (Folder 7)
    - United States
      - Civil Service Commission. Executive Seminar Center. Correspondence, printed material, 1970 (Folder 8)
      - Department of State
        - General (Folder 9)
        - Bureau of Public Affairs. Correspondence, 1967 (Folder 10)
        - Conference on East Asia. Notes, memoranda, conference participants, May, 1976 (Folder 11)
        - Personnel. Correspondence, memoranda, report, 1967 (Folder 12)
        - Senior Seminar on Foreign Policy. Correspondence, memoranda, notes, printed material, 1967-1971 (Folder 13)
      - Education. Printed material, 1968 (Folder 14)
      - Foreign relations
        - General. Japanese press summaries; "Why Policy Makers Do Not Listen" speech by Barbara Tuchman, American Foreign Service Association Luncheon,; printed materials; "The Role of the United States in World Affairs", speech by Secretary of State Dean Rusk, speech by Ambassador Arthur J. Goldberg, "The Carter Administration and Foreign Policy", speech by Charles S. Edwards, January 30, 1973 May l, 1967; May 12, 1967; April l8, 1977 (Folder 15-16)
        - Asia. "Political Realities in the Pacific Basin" by Claude Buss (?),; speech by Ambassador Graham Martin, news conference of President Richard Nixon, "The Nixon Doctrine, Japan and China: A Personal View from Japan" by Jun Tsunoda, Japanese press summaries, November 12, 1975 January 18, 1967; July 25, 1969; 1973; 1971 (Folder 17-18)
        - China. Speech by John S. Service, American Foreign Service Association,; "The United States and Communist China", speech by William P. Bundy, statement by Secretary of State Dean Rusk before the House Subcommittee on the Far East and the Pacific, printed materials, January 30, 1973 February 12, 1966; March 16, 1966; 1966 (Box 40, Folder 1)
        - Europe. "David Bruce's 'Long Telegram' of " by Martin F. Herz, July 3, 1951 1978 (Folder 2)
        - Japan. Memoranda (photocopies) from John K. Emmerson to the Department of State related to Japan and psychological warfare, sent from Yenan and Chungking,; memorandum from the American embassy, Chungking, "Kazuo Aoyama (Kuroda): Japanese 'Revolutionary'", printed materials, Japanese press summaries, study group papers, July-September, 1944 January 9, 1945; 1972-1977; 1972; 1973 (Folder 3-4)
        - Lebanon. Memorandum from John K. Emmerson on Lebanon, February 29, 1956 (Folder 5)
        - Middle East. Memorandum, "The Present Status of the Arab-Israeli Conflict", from John K. Emmerson to Department of State,; printed material, July 21, 1956 1967 (Folder 6)
      - Information Agency. Correspondence, list of participants in overseas speakers program, 1975-1976 (Folder 7)
      - Social conditions. "Disintegrating America -- Ecology of Crisis", by Yonosuke Nagai, September, 1970 (Folder 8)
    - U.S.-Japan Cooperative Medical Science Program. List of attendees, agenda, 1967 (Folder 9)
    - U.S.-Japan Seminar. Correspondence, list of participants, press release, notes, March 24-26, 1973 (Folder 10)
    - Vietnam (Folder 11)
      - Japanese press summaries, 1975-1978
      - Printed material, 1962-1967 (Folder 12-13)
      - Reports, press releases, memoranda (Box 41)
        - "Agreements of the Geneva Conference on Indo-China, Agreement on the Cessation of Hostilities in Viet-Nam", 1954. July (Folder 1)
        - "The Attacks on U.S. Ships in the Gulf of Tonkin and the Events That Followed During the Week, ", 1964. August 2-8, 1964 (Folder 2)
        - "Bombing North Viet-Nam"; "Concise History of Escalation in Viet-Nam"; "How Strong is the NLF?" by Douglas Pike; "The Myth of Civil War in Viet-Nam"; "Negotiation Attempts on Viet-Nam"; "Treatment of Civilian Casualties in Vietnam"; "Tuy Phuoc, Where Revolutionary Development is Succeeding", "United States Policy on Escalation in Viet-Nam"; "Viet-Nam Summary"; "Why We Are in Viet-Nam", U.S. Department of State publications, "Text of 'Declaration of Honolulu' issued by the United States and the Republic of Vietnam,; "Transcript of a News Conference by Cabinet-Level Officers of the United States and the Republic of Vietnam, "The Viet Cong and the People of South Viet-nam", "The American Effort in the Republic of Vietnam", memorandum for the record from Dwight H. Owen, Jr., "Vietnam, A Progress Report" from R.W. Komer to President Lyndon B. Johnson, statement by Ambassador Arthur J. Goldberg, text of address to the U.N. General Assembly by U.S. Ambassador Arthur J. Goldberg, "Programs of Assistance in South Vietnam Operated and Supported by U.S. Nonprofit Organizations", text of the Manila Conference Joint Communique, text of the Declaration of Peace and Progress in Asia and the Pacific, text of the 'Goals of Freedom' Declaration issued a the Manila Summit Conference, three statements of the Manila Summit Conference, "Viet-Nam and the International Law of Self-Defense", address by the Honorable Leonard C. Meeker, text of the letter delivered by Ambassador Arthur J. Goldberg to the Secretary General, Secretary Rusk's news conference, text of the letter from Ambassador Arthur J. Goldberg to the Secretary General, 1966. ca. 1966; February 8 February 7; April 4; September ll; September 13; September 22; September 22; October; October 25; October 25; October 25; October 25; December 13; December 19; December 21; December 31 (Folder 3-4)
        - Notes and parts of documents, background information for American Officials visiting Vietnam; "Comrade Vinh's Talk" (translation of North Vietnamese document); "Concise History of Escalation in Viet-Nam"; "Geneva Accords"; "JUSPAO Vietnam"; "Legal Status of South Viet-Nam"; "Information for Correspondents Visiting Da Nang"; "The Question of a Formal Declaration of War in Vietnam"; "Treatment of Civilian Casualties in Vietnam"; "The Viet Cong and the People of South Viet-Nam"; "Viet Nam: Civilian War Casualties"; "Vietnamese Constitutional Development"; "Vietnamese Political Dynamics", Letter from Dean Rusk to student leaders, (related correspondence, "Negotiation Attempts on Vietnam", "East Asia Today", address by William P. Bundy, Secretary Rusk's news conference, address by Ambassador Arthur J. Goldberg, memorandum from Anh Sau to Anh Tam (translation of North Vietnamese document, two copies), "Free World Assistance to Viet-Nam", "Seventeen Years in East Asia", address by the Honorable William P. Bundy, "Strengthening Vietnam's Government...The Training In-Put", "Views on Vietnam, by Dwight H. Owen, Jr., text of replies by Dean Rusk, "The Situation in Viet-Nam and U.S. Policy", address by William P. Bundy, additional remarks by William P. Bundy, statement of Secretary of Defense Robert P. McNamara, statement by the Department of State, Secretary Rusk's news conference, "Another Round in the Great Debate", address by Eugene V. Rostow, address by Nicholas Katzenbach, interview with Dean Rusk, "Southeast Asia: Area of Conflict and Tension", Foothill College, 1967. ca. 1967; January 4 January 24); January 6; January 20; February 9; February 10; March 7; April l; May 3; May 15; June 10; July 2; August 13; August 15; August 15; August 25; September 18; October 12; October 17; October 17; October 21; October 28 (Folder 5-6)
        - "After Ceasefire: The United States and the Outlook for East Asia", by Robert W. Barnett, 1972. December 20
    - War. "Modernized Societies and the Uses of War", Ambassador Francis T. Underhill, Jr., May, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Wilton Park. Correspondence, newsletter, conference information, printed material, 1973-1978 (Folder 2)
    - Woodrow Wilson Center. Correspondence, fellow and guest scholar appointments, printed materials, 1973 (Folder 3)
    - World Affairs Council. Correspondence, memoranda, printed materials, membership lists, conference information, programs
      - 1967 (Folder 4)
      - 1968 (Folder 5)
      - 1969 (Folder 6)
      - 1970 (Folder 7)
      - 1971 (Folder 8)
      - 1972 (Folder 9)
      - 1973 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      - 1974 (Folder 2)
      - 1975 (Folder 3)
      - 1976 (Folder 4)
      - 1977 (Folder 5)
      - 1978 (Folder 6)
      - 1979 (Folder 7)
      - 1981 (Folder 8)
      - 1982 (Folder 9)
      - 1983 (Folder 10)
    - World Population and Gross National Product. Charts (Folder 11)
- AUDIO-VISUAL.
  86 prints, 1 postcard, 1 negative, 3 slides / 2 envelopes
  - 55 prints of John K. Emmerson undated (Envelope A)
  - 20 prints of John Emmerson and others; 2 prints of John Emmerson; 1 print of Thomas Potter Davis; 5 unidentified prints; 3 prints of Mr. and Mrs. John Emmerson and others; 1 postcard; 1 negative; 3 slides, undated (Envelope B)
- Incremental materials (Box 44-85)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.